One billion people in the world today
يوجد في العالم اليوم مليار شخص
do not have access to all-season roads.
لا تتوفر له طرق صالحة للاستخدام في الفصول المختلفة.
One billion people.
مليار شخص.
One seventh of the Earth's population
سُبع سكان الأرض
are totally cut off for some part of the year.
معزولين تماماً لجزء من السنة.
We cannot get medicine to them reliably,
نحن لا نستطيع إيصال الدواء لهم بكفاءة،
they cannot get critical supplies,
لا يستطيعون الحصول على حاجيات أساسية،
and they cannot get their goods to market
و لا يستطيعون إيصال بضائعهم إلى السوق،
in order to create a sustainable income.
لإيجاد دخل مستمر.
In sub-Saharan Africa, for instance,
في جنوب الصحراء الكبرى الأفريقية، على سبيل المثال،
85 percent of roads are unusable in the wet season.
85% من الطرق غير صالحة للاستخدام في المواسم الممطرة.
Investments are being made,
يوجد استثمارات،
but at the current level,
لكن بناء على المستوى الحالي،
it's estimated it's going to take them
يقدر أنه سوف يستغرقهم الأمر
50 years to catch up.
50 سنة للحاق بالركب.
In the U.S. alone, there's more than four million
في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية وحدها، يوجد أكثر من أربعة ملايين
miles of roads, very expensive to build,
ميل من الطرق، التي يكلف بناؤها الكثير،
very expensive to maintain infrastructure,
و كذلك الإبقاء على بنيتها التحتية،
with a huge ecological footprint,
مع تأثير على البيئة كبير،
and yet, very often, congested.
و مع ذلك، فهي مزدحمة في أغلب الأحيان.
So we saw this and we thought,
لذا فقد رأينا هذا و فكرنا،
can there be a better way?
هل يوجد طريقة أفضل؟
Can we create a system using today's most advanced technologies
هل يمكننا ابتكار نظام باستخدام أحدث تكنولوجيا العصر
that can allow this part of the world to leapfrog
يمكنه أن يسمح لهذا الجزء من العالم أن يقفز قفزة نوعية
in the same way they've done with mobile telephones
كما فعلنا مع أجهزة الهاتف المحمول
in the last 10 years?
في السنوات الـ 10 الماضية؟
Many of those nations have excellent telecommunications today
إن العديد من هذه البلاد تمتلك اتصالات ممتازة اليوم
without ever putting copper lines in the ground.
دون وضع أسلاك نحاسية في الأرض أبداً.
Could we do the same for transportation?
هل يمكننا عمل الأمر ذاته مع النقل؟
Imagine this scenario.
تخيل هذا السيناريو.
Imagine you are in a maternity ward in Mali,
تخيل أنك في جناح الأمومة في مالي،
and have a newborn in need of urgent medication.
و لديك مولود جديد في حاجة لمساعدة طبية عاجلة.
What would you do today?
ماذا كنت لتفعل في عصرنا هذا؟
Well, you would place a request via mobile phone,
حسناً، كنت لتبعث بطلب عن طريق الهاتف المحمول،
and someone would get the request immediately.
و أحد ما سوف يصله الطلب فوراً.
That's the part that works.
هذا الجزء الذي ينجح.
The medication may take days to arrive, though,
لكن، الدواء قد يتحاج إلى أيام ليصل،
because of bad roads.
بسبب الطرق السيئة.
That's the part that's broken.
هذا الجزء الذي يفشل.
We believe we can deliver it within hours
نحن نعتقد أنا قادرون على إيصاله خلال ساعات.
with an electric autonomous flying vehicle
بواسطة مركبة كهربائية آلية طائرة
such as this.
كهذه.
This can transport a small payload today, about two kilograms,
هذه يمكنها نقل حِمل صغير اليوم، حوالي كيلوجرامين،
over a short distance, about 10 kilometers,
لمسافة قصيرة، حوالي 10 كيلومترات،
but it's part of a wider network that may cover
لكنها جزء من شبكة أوسع التي قد تغطي
the entire country, maybe even the entire continent.
البلد في الكامل، حتى من المحتمل القارة بأكملها.
It's an ultra-flexible, automated logistics network.
إنها شبكة فائقة المرونة، ذات تخطيط ذاتي.
It's a network for a transportation of matter.
إنها شبكة لنقل المادة.
We call it Matternet.
نحن نسميها بشبكة المادة.
We use three key technologies.
نحن نستخدم ثلاثة تقنيات حديثة أساسية.
The first is electric autonomous flying vehicles.
الأولى هي مركبة كهربائية ذاتية التحكم طائرة.
The second is automated ground stations
الثانية هي مراكز أرضية آلية
that the vehicles fly in and out of
حيث تطير المركبات منها و إليها
to swap batteries and fly farther,
لتبديل البطاريات و لتطير لمسافة أبعد،
or pick up or deliver loads.
أو لتحمل أو توصل أحمال.
And the third is the operating system
و الثالثة هو نظام تشغيل
that manages the whole network.
الذي يدير الشبكة كلها.
Let's look at each one of those technologies in a bit more detail.
دعنا ننظر إلى كل واحد كن هذه التقنيات بتفصيل أكثر بقليل.
First of all, the UAVs.
أولاً، الطائرات بلا طيار.
Eventually, we're going to be using all sorts of vehicles
في النهاية، نحن سوف نستخدم كل أنواع المركبات
for different payload capacities and different ranges.
من أجل طاقات استيعاب أحمال مختلفة و لمسافات مختلفة.
Today, we're using small quads.
إننا اليوم نستخدم مركبات رباعية صغيرة.
These are able to transport two kilograms
إنها قادرة على توصيل كيلوجرامين من الأحمال
over 10 kilometers in just about 15 minutes.
لمسافة أكثر من 10 كيلومترات في 15 دقيقة.
Compare this with trying to trespass a bad road
قارن ذلك بمحاولة اجتياز طريق وعرة
in the developing world,
في العالم النامي،
or even being stuck in traffic
أو حتى أن تكون عالق بالازدحام
in a developed world country.
في بلد في العالم المتطور.
These fly autonomously.
هذه تطير بشكل آلي.
This is the key to the technology.
هذا هو أساس التقنية الحديثة.
So they use GPS and other sensors on board
إذاً فهي تستخدم جهاز الملاحة و حسّاسات أخرى في المركبة
to navigate between ground stations.
لتتنقل بين المحطات الأرضية.
Every vehicle is equipped with an automatic
كل مركبة مجهزة بألية ذاتية
payload and battery exchange mechanism,
لتحميل الأحمال و تبديل البطارية،
so these vehicles navigate to those ground stations,
إذاً هذه المركبات تجد طريقها لهذه المحطات الأرضية،
they dock, swap a battery automatically,
تهبط، تغير بطاريتها آلياً
and go out again.
و تنطلق من جديد.
The ground stations are located on safe locations
إن المحطات الأرضية موجودة في أماكن آمنة
on the ground.
على الأرض.
They secure the most vulnerable part of the mission,
إنها تؤمن أكثر جزء حساس في المهمة،
which is the landing.
و هو الهبوط.
They are at known locations on the ground,
إنها في أماكن معروفة على الأرض،
so the paths between them are also known,
إذاً المسارات بينها معلومة أيضاً،
which is very important from a reliability perspective
الأمر المهم جداً من منظور الكفاءة
from the whole network.
للشبكة كلها.
Apart from fulfilling the energy requirements of the vehicles,
بالإضافة إلى التزود بمتطلبات المركبة من الطاقة،
eventually they're going to be becoming
في النهاية إنهم سوف يصبحون
commercial hubs where people can take out loads
محاور تجارية حيث يستطيع الناس أخذ أحمال من
or put loads into the network.
أو وضعها في الشبكة.
The last component is the operating system
الجزء الأخير هو نظام التشغيل
that manages the whole network.
الذي يدير كل الشبكة.
It monitors weather data from all the ground stations
إنه يتابع بيانات الطقس من كل محطات الأرضية
and optimizes the routes of the vehicles through the system
و يجد أفضل الطرق للمركبة خلال النظام
to avoid adverse weather conditions,
لتجنب الأحوال الجوية السيئة،
avoid other risk factors,
و تجنب عوامل مخاطرة أخرى،
and optimize the use of the resources
و يجد أفضل الطرق لاستخدام الموارد
throughout the network.
خلال الشبكة.
I want to show you what one of those flights
أريد أن أريك كيف تبدو أحد هذه
looks like.
الرحلات الطائرة.
Here we are flying in Haiti last summer,
هنا نحن نطير في هاييتي الصيف الماضي،
where we've done our first field trials.
حيث أجرينا تجاربنا الحقلية الأولى.
We're modeling here a medical delivery
هنا نحن نعرض توصيل المواد الطبية
in a camp we set up after the 2010 earthquake.
في مخيم قد أنشأناه بعد الزلزال عام 2010
People there love this.
إن الناس هناك يحبوها.
And I want to show you
و أود أن أريكم
what one of those vehicles looks like up close.
كيف تبدو أحد هذه المركبات عن قرب.
So this is a $3,000 vehicle.
إذاً هذه مركبة تقدربـ 3000$.
Costs are coming down very rapidly.
إن التكاليف في انخفاض سريع جداً.
We use this in all sorts of weather conditions,
نحن نستخدم هذه في كل الأحوال الجوية،
very hot and very cold climates,
المناخات الحارة جداً و الباردة جداً،
very strong winds. They're very sturdy vehicles.
في الرياح القوية جداُ. إنها مركبات متينة جداً.
Imagine if your life depended on this package,
تخيل إن كانت حياتك تعتمد على هذه الرزمة،
somewhere in Africa
في مكان ما في أفريقيا
or in New York City, after Sandy.
أو في نيويورك، بعد إعصار ساندي.
The next big question is, what's the cost?
السؤال المهم التالي هو، ما هي التكلفة؟
Well, it turns out that the cost to transport
حسناً، تبين أن التكلفة لنقل
two kilograms over 10 kilometers with this vehicle
كيلوجرامان لمسافة أطول من 10 كيلومترات بهذه المركبة
is just 24 cents.
هي 24 سنت فقط.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And it's counterintuitive, but the cost of energy
و إنه أمر تقديري، لكن تكلفة الطاقة
expended for the flight is only two cents
التي تصرف على الرحلة هي سنتين فقط
of a dollar today,
من الدولار اليوم،
and we're just at the beginning of this.
و نحن فقط في بدايات الأمر.
When we saw this, we felt that this is something
عندما رأينا هذا، لقد شعرنا أن هذا أمر
that can have significant impact in the world.
يمكن أن يكون له تأثير كبير في العالم.
So we said, okay, how much does it cost
فقلنا، حسناً، كم هي تكلفة
to set up a network somewhere in the world?
إنشاء شبكة في مكان ما من العالم؟
And we looked at setting up a network in Lesotho
و نظرنا في إنشاء شبكة في ليسوتو
for transportation of HIV/AIDS samples.
لنقل عينات للإيدز/فيروس الإيدز.
The problem there is how do you take them
إن المشكلة في الأمر هي كيف تأخذها
from clinics where they're being collected
من العيادات حيث تُجمع
to hospitals where they're being analyzed?
إلى المستشفيات حيث تُحلل؟
And we said, what if we wanted to cover an area
و قلنا، ماذا لو أردنا أن نغطي منطقة
spanning around 140 square kilometers?
تمتد لـ140 كيلومتر مربع؟
That's roughly one and a half times the size of Manhattan.
هذا حوالي مرة و نصف مساحة منهاتن.
Well it turns out that the cost to do that there
حسناً لقد تبين أن تكلفة ذلك هناك
would be less than a million dollars.
سوف تكون أقل من مليون دولار.
Compare this to normal infrastructure investments.
قارن هذا باستثمارات البنية التحتية العادية.
We think this can be -- this is the power
نحن نعتقد أن ذلك يمكن أن يكون – هذه هي القوة
of a new paradigm.
في النموذج الحديث.
So here we are: a new idea
إذاً فنحن هاهنا: فكرة جديدة
about a network for transportation
عن شبكة نقل
that is based on the ideas of the Internet.
المعتمدة على أفكار مستوحاة من الإنترنت.
It's decentralized, it's peer-to-peer,
إنها لا مركزية، تصل بين شخص و الآخر،
it's bidirectional, highly adaptable,
إنها ثنائية الاتجاه، قابلة للتأقلم بشكل كبير،
with very low infrastructure investment,
مع تكاليف منخفضة جداً للبنية التحتية،
very low ecological footprint.
و تأثير بيئي ضئيل جداً.
If it is a new paradigm, though,
إنه نموذج جديد، لكن،
there must be other uses for it.
يجب أن يكون له استخدامات أخرى.
It can be used perhaps in other places in the world.
قد يمكن استخدامه في أماكن أخرى من العالم.
So let's look at the other end of the spectrum:
إذاً دعنا ننظر إلى الناحية الأخرى من الموضوع:
our cities and megacities.
مدننا و مدننا الكبيرة.
Half of the Earth's population lives in cities today.
نصف سكان الأرض يعيشون في المدن اليوم.
Half a billion of us live in megacities.
نصف مليار منا يعيش في مدن كبيرة.
We are living through an amazing urbanization trend.
نحن نعيش خلال نزعة مدنية رائعة.
China alone is adding a megacity
إن الصين وحدها تقوم بإضافة مدينة كبيرة
the size of New York City every two years.
بحجم مدينة نيويورك كل سنتين.
These are places that do have road infrastructure,
هذه أماكن تحتوي على بنية تحتية للطرق،
but it's very inefficient.
لكنها ليست فعالة بشكل كبير.
Congestion is a huge problem.
احتقان الشوارع مشكلة هائلة.
So we think it makes sense in those places
إذاً نحن نعتقد أن الحل المنطقي في هذه المناطق
to set up a network of transportation
هو إنشاء شبكة للنقل
that is a new layer that sits between the road
التي هي طبقة جديدة بين الطريق
and the Internet,
و شبكة الانترنت،
initially for lightweight, urgent stuff,
في البداية للأغراض الخفيفة، الطارئة،
and over time, we would hope to develop this
و مع الوقت، نحن نأمل بتطوير هذه
into a new mode of transportation
لتصبح وسيلة جديدة للمواصلات
that is truly a modern solution to a very old problem.
التي هي حقاً حل عصري لمشكلة قديمة جداً.
It's ultimately scalable
إنها في النهاية قابلة للتحجيم
with a very small ecological footprint,
مع تأثير على البيئة صغير جداً،
operating in the background 24/7,
و هي تعمل في الخلفية 24 ساعة 7 أيام في الأسبوع،
just like the Internet.
تماماً كالإنترنت.
So when we started this
إذاً عندما بدأنا هذا
a couple of years ago now,
منذ بضعة سنوات من الآن،
we've had a lot of people come up to us who said,
جاءنا الكثير من الناس الذين قالوا لنا:
"This is a very interesting but crazy idea,
"هذه فكرة مثيرة جداً للاهتمام لكنها مجنونة،
and certainly not something that you should
و بالطبع ليست أمراً يجب عليك
engage with anytime soon."
العمل عليه في الزمن القريب."
And of course, we're talking about drones, right,
و بالطبع، نحن نتكلم عن طائرات بدون طيار، صحيح،
a technology that's not only unpopular in the West
هي تقنية ليست فقط غير شعبية في الغرب
but one that has become a very, very unpleasant
لكنها تقنية قد أصبحت حقيقة مكروهة جداً، جداً
fact of life for many living in poor countries,
في حياة الكثيرين الذين يعيشون في البلدان الفقيرة،
especially those engaged in conflict.
بالأخص تلك المرتبطة بصراع.
So why are we doing this?
إذاً لماذا نحن نفعل هذا؟
Well, we chose to do this one
حسناً، لقد اخترنا هذه التقنية
not because it's easy,
ليس لأنها سهلة،
but because it can have amazing impact.
لكن لأنه يمكنها امتلاك تأثير رائع.
Imagine one billion people being connected
تخيل مليار شخص متصل
to physical goods in the same way
بالبضائع الملموسة بنفس الطريقة
that mobile telecommunications connected them
التي ربطتهم بها الاتصالات المتنقلة
to information.
بالمعلومات.
Imagine if the next big network we built in the world
تخيل إن كانت الشبكة الكبرى التالية التي بنيناها في العالم
was a network for the transportation of matter.
كانت شبكة لنقل المادة.
In the developing world, we would hope
في العالم النامي، نحن نأمل
to reach millions of people with better vaccines,
أن نصل لملايين من الناس مع تطعيمات أفضل،
reach them with better medication.
أن نصل إليهم مع أدوية أفضل.
It would give us an unfair advantage against battling
إنها سوف تعطينا ميزة غير عادلة في صراعنا مع
HIV/AIDS, tuberculosis and other epidemics.
الإيدز/فيروس الإيدز، السل و الأوبئة الأخرى.
Over time, we would hope it would become
مع مرور الوقت، نحن نتمنى أن تصبح
a new platform for economic transactions,
منصة جديدة للتداولات الاقتصادية،
lifting millions of people out of poverty.
و انتشال الملايين من الناس من الفقر.
In the developed world and the emerging world,
في العالم المتطور و في العالم النامي،
we would hope it would become a new mode
نحن نتمنى أن تصبح وسيلة جديدة
of transportation that could help make our cities
للنقل يمكنها المساعدة في جعل مدننا
more livable.
أكثر قابلية للسكن.
So for those that still believe that this is science fiction,
إذاً لهؤلاء الذين لا يزالون يعتقدون أن هذا خيال علمي،
I firmly say to you that it is not.
إنني أؤكد لكم أنه ليس كذلك.
We do need to engage, though,
نحن بحاجة لأن نتفاعل، على الرغم من ذلك،
in social fiction to make it happen.
في الخيال الاجتماعي لجعل الأمر واقع.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)